<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title type="text">What If?</title>
	<id>http://what-if.xkcd.com/feed.atom</id>
	<link href="http://what-if.xkcd.com/feed.atom" rel="self" />
	<author>
		<name>xkcd</name>
		<email>whatif@xkcd.com</email>
	</author>
	<icon>http://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/favicon.ico</icon>
	<logo>http://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/favicon.ico</logo>
	<subtitle type="text">Answering your hypothetical questions with physics, every Tuesday.</subtitle>
	<entry>
		<id>http://what-if.xkcd.com/156/</id>
		<title type="text">Electrofishing for Whales</title>
		<updated>2017-03-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<author>
			<name>xkcd</name>
			<email>whatif@xkcd.com</email>
		</author>
		<content type="html">&lt;article class="entry"&gt;
  &lt;a href="//what-if.xkcd.com/156/"&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Electrofishing for Whales&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p id="question"&gt;I used to work on a fisheries crew where we would use an electro-fisher backpack to momentarily stun small fish (30 - 100 mm length) so we could scoop them up with nets to identify and measure them. The larger fish tended to be stunned for slightly longer because of their larger surface area but I don&amp;#39;t imagine this relationship would be maintained for very large animals. Could you electrofish for a blue whale? At what voltage would you have have to set the e-fisher?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="attribute"&gt;&#8212;Madeline Cooper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you want to give endangered whales powerful electric shocks. Great! I&amp;#39;m happy to help. This is definitely a very normal thing to want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various electrofishing setups, but they all operate on the same general principle: An electric current flows through the water, and also through any fish that happen to be in the water. The electric current, through a few different physical effects, draws the fish toward one of the electrodes and/or stuns them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="I&amp;#39;m just gonna set my drink on the safety switch so I can rest my eyes for a few. You have fun." src="/imgs/a/156/setup.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, people didn&amp;#39;t really notice that electrofishing injured fish at all. For the most part, stunned fish seemed to be fine after a few minutes. However, they frequently suffer from internal damage which isn&amp;#39;t obvious from the outside. The electric current causes involuntary muscle spasms, which can fracture the fish&amp;#39;s vertebrae. As &lt;a href="http://opensample.info/effect-of-electrofishing-pulse-shape-and-electrofishing-induced-spinal-injury-on-long-term-growth-and-survival-of-wild-rainbow-trout"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; shows, these kinds of spinal injuries are more common and severe in larger fish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you mention, for a given electrofishing setup, larger fish are usually more affected than smaller ones.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;This can lead to larger fish being overrepresented in sampling studies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Why? Well, we don&amp;#39;t know. In their comprehensive 2003 study &lt;em&gt;Immobilization Thresholds of Electrofishing Relative to Fish Size&lt;/em&gt;, biologists Chad Dolan and Steve Miranda modeled the way electric currents stun fish of different sizes, but caution that &amp;quot;no adequate conceptual system exists to explain the effects of size on electroshock thresholds from the perspective of electric fields.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these studies dealt with animals anywhere near the size of whales. The largest fish in Dolan and Miranda&amp;#39;s study were still quite small. &lt;a href="http://electrofishing.net/2016/01/23/535/"&gt;This experiment&lt;/a&gt; tested larger fish up to 80cm long,&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;The fish they used in the experiment grew rapidly to a range of sizes, mainly because the larger ones kept eating their smaller siblings.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; but nothing whale-sized.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;There&amp;#39;s been at least &lt;a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2015/02/150217-irrawaddy-dolphins-myanmar-electro-fishing-mandalay/"&gt;one case&lt;/a&gt; of dolphin death linked to illegal electrofishing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Since we don&amp;#39;t know exactly why larger fish respond differently, it&amp;#39;s hard to confidently extrapolate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fish are &lt;a href="https://nctc.fws.gov/courses/CSP/CSP2C01/resources/5-Power-Transfer-Theory-Standardization/2_Electrofishing,%20A%20Power%20Related%20Phenomenon.pdf"&gt;typically&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[4]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;Actual quote from that paper: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The results for these tests were unsettling ... this observation was so unexpected that we stopped the experiment to recalibrate the equipment.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; stunned by equipment delivering about 100 &#181;W of power per cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; of body volume, so for a whale, that would be about 20 megawatts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;#39;s a catch: Most electrofishing is done in fresh water. Unfortunately, blue whales live in the ocean,&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[5]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;I mean, unfortunately for Madeline. It&amp;#39;s fortunate for the whales.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; where the salt water conducts electricity much more easily. That might seem like good news for our electrofishing plans, but it turns out to make it much more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrofishing works best when the water and the target animals are about equally conductive. In highly conductive saltwater, most of the current flows past the animals in the water rather than through them. This means that ocean electrofishing requires much more power. Using our simple extrapolation, instead of 20 megawatts, we might need a gigawatt. In other words, you&amp;#39;ll need to bring a large nuclear generating station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="All right, I&amp;#39;m just gonna nap here, but let me know when you&amp;#39;ve ordered a container ship on Amazon or whatever." src="/imgs/a/156/boat.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple extrapolation is misleading here, since we know that large animals respond to electricity differently. How differently? Well, according to an &lt;a href="http://electrofishing.net/2015/12/30/man-overboard/"&gt;electrofishing.net post&lt;/a&gt; by Jan Dean, a human who fell into the water in front of a typical electrofishing boat could easily die.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[6]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;While it sounds dangerous, people aren&amp;#39;t often killed during electrofishing accidents. The 2000 EPA report &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyNET.exe/30003TAI.TXT?ZyActionD=ZyDocument&amp;amp;Client=EPA&amp;amp;Index=1995+Thru+1999&amp;amp;Docs=&amp;amp;Query=&amp;amp;Time=&amp;amp;EndTime=&amp;amp;SearchMethod=1&amp;amp;TocRestrict=n&amp;amp;Toc=&amp;amp;TocEntry=&amp;amp;QField=&amp;amp;QFieldYear=&amp;amp;QFieldMonth=&amp;amp;QFieldDay=&amp;amp;IntQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;ExtQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;XmlQuery=&amp;amp;File=D%3A%5Czyfiles%5CIndex%20Data%5C95thru99%5CTxt%5C00000016%5C30003TAI.txt&amp;amp;User=ANONYMOUS&amp;amp;Password=anonymous&amp;amp;SortMethod=h%7C-&amp;amp;MaximumDocuments=1&amp;amp;FuzzyDegree=0&amp;amp;ImageQuality=r75g8/r75g8/x150y150g16/i425&amp;amp;Display=hpfr&amp;amp;DefSeekPage=x&amp;amp;SearchBack=ZyActionL&amp;amp;Back=ZyActionS&amp;amp;BackDesc=Results%20page&amp;amp;MaximumPages=1&amp;amp;ZyEntry=1&amp;amp;SeekPage=x&amp;amp;ZyPURL#"&gt;New Perspectives in Electrofishing&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; comments that &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;In the United States, since World War II, only about five electrocutions during electrofishing have been documented.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; I assume they just mean records weren&amp;#39;t kept before World War II, but it&amp;#39;s technically possible that the war involved so many electrofishing deaths that they need to exclude it from the stats.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Blue whales, which are even larger than humans,&lt;sup&gt;[&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetacean"&gt;citation needed&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt; would presumably fare even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="Now I want to manufacture tiny defibrillator paddles and mount them in busy coral reefs." src="/imgs/a/156/arrest.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrofishing temporarily &lt;a href="https://eurekamag.com/pdf.php?pdf=004141382"&gt;stops a fish&amp;#39;s heart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[7]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;Until reading this paper, I didn&amp;#39;t know clove oil was used as a fish anesthetic. You learn something new every day!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The fish seem to recover, most of the time, but humans&#8212;and probably whales&#8212;have a harder time with cardiac arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s possible that giving blue whales massive electrical shocks isn&amp;#39;t as good an idea as it sounded at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s not to say there&amp;#39;s no place in science for giving random electric shocks to large aquatic animals. &lt;a href="https://www.aphis.usda.gov/wildlife_damage/nwrc/symposia/repellents_symposium/pdfs/kolz.pdf"&gt;A project&lt;/a&gt; at the Denver Wildlife Research Center used electrofishing-style equipment&#8212;linked to an infrared camera&#8212;to repel beavers, ducks, and geese from selected areas. Apparently, the results were &amp;quot;encouraging.&amp;quot;&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[8]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;The equipment kept the beavers away, although they returned as soon as it was turned off. It also worked on ducks and geese, although they had some problems with infrared waterfowl detection. The birds would usually take flight when the equipment turned on, although if it was cold enough, they&amp;#39;d just sluggishly paddle away.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So electrofishing equipment probably can&amp;#39;t help you catch blue whales. However, if you&amp;#39;re having trouble keeping them out of your backyard pond ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="Sure, kids, they look like cute pets when they&amp;#39;re 5-ton calves, but before you know it they&amp;#39;ll be 150-ton adults who need all your time and attention!" src="/imgs/a/156/pond.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... it&amp;#39;s possible the Denver Wildlife Research Center can help you out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
		</content>
		<link href="http://what-if.xkcd.com/156/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
		<published>2017-03-09T00:00:00Z</published>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<id>http://what-if.xkcd.com/155/</id>
		<title type="text">Toaster vs. Freezer</title>
		<updated>2017-02-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<author>
			<name>xkcd</name>
			<email>whatif@xkcd.com</email>
		</author>
		<content type="html">&lt;article class="entry"&gt;
  &lt;a href="//what-if.xkcd.com/155/"&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Toaster vs. Freezer&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p id="question"&gt;Would a toaster still work in a freezer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="attribute"&gt;&#8212;&lt;a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/shows/my-brother-my-brother-and-me"&gt;My Brother, My Brother and Me&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/my-brother-my-brother-and-me/mbmbam-343-sauce-doctors-blessing"&gt;Episode 343&lt;/a&gt;, discussing a Yahoo Answers question&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/my-brother-my-brother-and-me/mbmbam-343-sauce-doctors-blessing"&gt;a recent episode&lt;/a&gt; of Justin, Travis, and Griffin McElroy&amp;#39;s terrific advice podcast, &lt;em&gt;My Brother, My Brother and Me&lt;/em&gt;, the brothers pondered a Yahoo Answers question about what would happen if you put a toaster inside a freezer. (The discussion comes around the 36-minute mark.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have a fun discussion of a few aspects of the problem before eventually moving on to the next question. Since they don&amp;#39;t really settle on a final answer, I thought we could help them out by taking a closer look at the physics of freezer toasters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="Your ice cream has ... toaster burn?" src="/imgs/a/155/setup.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(A quick safety note: If you actually do this, keep in mind that the toaster may melt some of the ice in the freezer, leaving you with a running electrical appliance in a pool of water.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Griffin sums up the situation like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;You put a toaster in a freezer. You run the extension cord in there. You put some good bread in there. You click it down. What even &lt;strong&gt;happens&lt;/strong&gt;, right? Because if your answer is, "it would get hot," then the freezer hasn't done its job. But if you say "it would get cold," then the toaster hasn't done &lt;strong&gt;its&lt;/strong&gt; job.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, the answer: The toaster would win. The freezer wouldn&amp;#39;t do its job. Toasters beat freezers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="The effect of freezers on bread turns out to be something everyone on the internet has an opinion on, so I try to avoid the subject by just eating all my bread as soon as I get it." src="/imgs/a/155/power.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s easy to think of a toaster and freezer as equivalent&#8212;one cools things down and the other warms them up. But toasters heat things up a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more than freezers cool them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coils in regular toasters get hot enough to glow, which means they&amp;#39;re over about 600&#176;C. Since the toaster is operating at such high temperatures, it would hardly notice whether the surrounding environment is 20&#176;C (room temperature), 4&#176;C (a fridge), or -15&#176;C (a freezer).&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;The zero on our usual temperature scales can confuse things, since it makes it seem like going from 10&#176; to 20&#176; is &amp;quot;doubling&amp;quot; the temperature. But the &amp;quot;zero&amp;quot; on the Celsius scale is just a point chosen by convention. If we switch to Kelvin, which counts in degrees above absolute zero, a freezer is 260 K, a fridge is 275 K, a normal room is 295 K ... and the heating element in a toaster is 900 K.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="[the markings on the worst thermostat dial ever]" src="/imgs/a/155/relative.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toaster needs to heat its coils from room temperature to somewhere over 600&#176;C. From the toaster&amp;#39;s point of view, a 20- or 40-degree change in starting temperature hardly matters. The coils will get hot, and then the bread will get hot, too. If the bread is colder at the start, the toaster will have to heat it a little longer to get it up to ideal toasting temperature, but it will have no trouble getting there. As anyone who&amp;#39;s ever burned a piece of toast knows, toasters are definitely capable of heating bread to above the ideal temperature for toast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their discussion, the McElroys brought up another question: Even if the toaster can still toast bread at first, would it struggle to stay warm over time? If you left both the toaster and the freezer running, who would win in the long term?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that the toaster would still win. A toaster produces about a thousand watts of heat, and the cooling system in a household freezer can&amp;#39;t remove heat that fast. In fact, since freezers are so well insulated, the inside of the freezer would probably get much hotter than the rest of the house, and eventually the toaster and/or the freezer would probably overheat.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;Either device have a safety cutoff that stops things from actually melting down, but it&amp;#39;s probably not wise to count on that in this situation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refrigerators and freezers work by soaking up heat from their interior and dumping it out the back.&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;That&amp;#39;s why the area behind your freezer is warm, and why you can&amp;#39;t cool a room by leaving the fridge door open.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; In a sense, they&amp;#39;re more efficient than toasters. Fridges have a &amp;quot;coefficient of performance&amp;quot; of 2 or 3, which means it only takes them 1 unit of electrical energy to move 2 or 3 units of heat energy from the interior to the exterior. A toaster, on the other hand, produces 1 unit of heat from 1 unit of electricity. But since the compressor in a fridge-freezer typically only uses 100 or 150 watts when it&amp;#39;s running,&lt;span class="ref"&gt;&lt;span class="refnum"&gt;[4]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="refbody"&gt;You can see some real-world graphs of refrigerator power usage, courtesy people with home electricity meters, with &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=fridge+watts+monitor+graph"&gt;a simple Google Image search&lt;/a&gt;. The distinctive on-off square-wave pattern is the compressor switching on and off throughout the day, while the big spikes are the heating element that keeps frost from building up on the coils. This power consumption is split between the fridge and the freezer, but if the fridge is already cold, most of the energy will be spent fighting with the toaster.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; so even with the efficiency multiplier, it can&amp;#39;t keep up with the toaster&amp;#39;s 1000+ watts of heat production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the toaster will start to heat up the inside of the freezer. Even if the freezer were as powerful as the toaster, it wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to keep the toaster coils themselves from getting hot and toasting bread. The freezer can make the air around the toaster cold, but remember, to the toaster, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our air is cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="Forget it, I&amp;#39;m going to hang out with that microwave instead." src="/imgs/a/155/neg.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you happen to live in the Canadian city of Winnipeg, you can check this experimentally. The winter temperature at night in Winnipeg is about the same as the inside of a freezer, so the environment there effectively simulates a freezer with infinite capacity to absorb heat. Suppose you put a toaster out on your porch one night, plugged in by an extension cord, and leave it running for a few hours, going outside every so often to collect the toast and put in some fresh bread. What will happen? Simple: You&amp;#39;ll quickly be eaten by wolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="&amp;#39;Doing a postdoc&amp;#39; is a Canadian euphemism for fighting off a wolf pack." src="/imgs/a/155/canada.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But assuming you survive the experiment, you should find that the toaster doesn&amp;#39;t have trouble working in the cold air. It may take a bit longer to get the bread properly browned, but unless the wind is extremely strong, it should be able to manage it fine. After all, to a toaster, all weather is cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between what humans consider &amp;quot;cold&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;warm&amp;quot; is negligible in a lot of high-temperature processes. For example, Antarctica has a &lt;a href="http://www.antarcticfire.org/"&gt;well-equipped fire department&lt;/a&gt;. It might seem strange to worry about things getting too hot in the coldest place on Earth, but fire poses a &lt;a href="http://www.coolantarctica.com/Antarctica%20fact%20file/science/antarctica_fire_history.php"&gt;serious threat&lt;/a&gt; to the researchers there. After all, the place is dry, windy, and doesn&amp;#39;t have a lot of liquid water sitting around to douse a flame with. Sure, it&amp;#39;s cold&#8212;but to a fire, &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; is cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are no wolves in Antarctica. So as long as you don&amp;#39;t mind a trip&#8212;and you get clearance from the Antarctica fire department&#8212;you can go there to enjoy your outdoor freezer toast in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="illustration" title="For the record, I&amp;#39;ve never been to Winnipeg and have nothing against it! I hear from survivors that it&amp;#39;s lovely." src="/imgs/a/155/antarctica.png"&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
		</content>
		<link href="http://what-if.xkcd.com/155/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
		<published>2017-02-28T00:00:00Z</published>
	</entry>
</feed>